Guide to the Lewis and Clark Expedition Maps and Receipt
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Lewis and Clark Expedition maps and receipt
1803-1810
WA MSS 303-304
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
2.68
(2 boxes)
The collection consists of 83 manuscript maps and related material on 66 sheets, dating from ca. 1803 to 1810. The maps detail the route of the Lewis and Clark Expedition to the Pacific Coast and back, 1804-1806. Many of them were created or annotated during the expedition by William Clark. A sketch map of Vancouver's Island and the region of Nootka Sound has been attributed to Captain Lewis. Several of the maps include information supplied by Native Americans. The collection also includes Clark's large map of 1810 which describes the continent from the Mississippi Valley to the Pacific. Three of the maps were drawn on the back of a manuscript list of supplies for the expedition, and two copies of a printed form intended to be distributed to Indian leaders encountered by the Expedition. There is also a receipt for compensation of the members of the expedition (WA MSS 304).
Clark, William, 1770-1838
Lewis, Meriwether, 1774-1809
Immediate Source of Acquisition
In 1903 the maps were the property of William Clark's heirs Julia Clark Voorhis and Eleanor Glasgow Voorhis. Julia Clark Voorhis willed the maps to her attorney, and upon his death his widow sold them to the Old Print Shop. They were acquired by Edward Eberstadt & Sons, who sold them to William Robertson Coe. Coe donated the collection to the Yale Library in 1951.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The Lewis and Clark Expedition Maps consist of 83 manuscript maps and related material on 66 sheets, dating from ca. 1803 to 1810. Nine of the maps (including one of Vancouver's Island and the region of Nootka Sound that appears to be in the hand of Lewis) were copied or otherwise obtained by Lewis and Clark in preparation for their expedition (folders 1, 4-9, 11, and 52). Many of these were annotated during the expedition. Two of the maps were drawn based on information supplied by the Mandan leader Big White, also known as Sheheke, at Fort Mandan during the winter of 1804-1805 (folder 10, r and v). Seventy of the maps, several of which include information supplied by Native Americans, were drawn by Clark in the field (folders 3v, 12-51, 53-65). Finally, two of the maps (folders 2 and 66) were prepared by Clark after the expedition's return. The map in folder 2, which Reuben Gold Thwaites mistakenly described as a pre-expeditionary map, is a virtual copy of a part of the map in folder 66, Clark's master map of the West which he drafted in 1810. 51" x 29" in size, the map incorporates information not only from the Lewis and Clark expedition but also from the travels of Zebulon Pike, George Drouillard, and John Colter. The map was the source for the smaller, engraved map published with Biddle's edition of the Lewis and Clark journals in 1814. The master map was returned to Clark who later added information from such travellers as Wilson Price Hunt, Andrew Henry, and possibly Ramsay Crooks. Three of the maps were drawn on the back of paper used for other purposes. Thus the collection includes a manuscript list of supplies for the expedition and two copies of a printed form intended to be distributed to Indian leaders who assisted the expedition.
These maps were kept in the Clark family after the majority of material from the expedition had been placed at the American Philosophical Society or the Missouri Historical Society. Reuben Gold Thwaites learned of the existence of the maps while working on an edition of the Lewis and Clark journals in 1903. Thwaites obtained permission from Julia Clark Voorhis and Eleanor Glasgow Voorhis to publish most of the maps as 53 numbered plates in the atlas that accompanied his Original Journals of the Lewis & Clark Expedition, published in 1904-1905 (New York: Dodd, Mead & Company). Thwaites found various of the Voorhis maps pasted together, creating continuous maps of several parts of the journey. The size of the multi-sheet map caused Thwaites to reproduce them in multiple plates. Eighty years later, as Gary E. Moulton prepared a new edition of the Lewis & Clark journals, he determined that the pasted arrangement obscured original data and that the joining of sheets was clearly a postexpeditionary event. The Library decided to separate the sheets, which were then photographed for reproduction in the Moulton atlas.
The maps are arranged in the sequence of the Thwaites atlas. The folder descriptions in this listing, however, are taken from Gary E. Moulton's atlas, except for those maps not included in Moulton: in those cases the Thwaites description is used. Each folder number represents a separate sheet. In the case of those sheets with a map on both the recto and verso, the single sheet has two separate entries distinguished by a "r" or "v" after a folder number, indicating the recto or verso of the sheet. In addition to the listing by box and folder number, there is an appendix providing a concordance for Moulton numbers and box and folder numbers.
Appendix I. Moulton Concordance
Moulton Folder number number
3a........3v
4.........1
7.........4
8.........5
9.........6
10........7
11........8
12........9
30........11
31a.......10r
31b.......10v
33........21r
34........21v
35........22r
36........22v
37........23r
38........23v
39........24r
40........24v
41........26r
42........26v
43........25r
44........25v
45........25r
46........12
47........13
48........14
49........15
50........16
51........17
52........18
53........19
54........20
62........27
63........28
64........29
65........30r
66........30v
67........31
68........32
69........33
70........34
71........35
72........36
73........37
74........38
75........39
76........40
77........41
78........42
79........43
80........44
81........45
82........46
83........47
84........48
85........49
86........50r
87........54v
88........50v
89........51r
90........53v
91........51v
92........51v
93........53r
94........53r
96........54r
98........55r
99........55v
100.......56v
101.......56r
103.......57v
104.......58
105.......59v
106.......60
107.......61
108.......62
110.......63
111.......64
112.......65
125.......66
Indian cartography -- North America; West (U.S.) -- Maps; Maps -- United States; Cartographers -- United States; Soldiers -- United States; Clark, William, 1770-1838; Lewis, Meriwether, 1774-1809; Lewis and Clark Expedition ( 1804-1806)
- Expedition Maps (WA MSS 303)
  Scope and Contents
  The Expedition Maps are arranged, as they were when they arrived at the Beinecke, according to numbers given in Reuben Gold Thwaites' atlas to the Original Journals of the Lewis & Clark Expedition, published in 1904-05. The folder descriptions, however, are taken from Gary E. Moulton's 1983 Atlas of the Lewis & Clark Expedition. Each folder number represents a separate sheet. In the case of those sheets with a map on both the recto and verso, the single sheet has two separate entries distinguished by a "r" or "v" after a folder number, indicating the recto or verso of the sheet.
  - Soulard's Map of 1795 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Caption title: "A Topogr[aphical] Sketch of the Missouri and Upper Mississippi, Exhibiting The various Nations and Tribes of Indians who inhabit the Country: Copied from the original Spanish MS Map."
    Thwaites 2, Moulton 4
  - The Upper Mississippi system, and the Missouri system as far as the Mandans. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Thwaites 3, not in Moulton
  - "A Memorandum of Articles in readiness for the Voyage," manuscript list (Box 1, Folder 3r)
  - Clark's Map of the Grand Tower, route about November 25, 1803 (Box 1, Folder 3v)
    Thwaites 4, Moulton 3a
  - Evans's Map 1 (the Expedition's route about August 13-September 10, 1804) (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Thwaites 5, Moulton 7
  - Evans's Map 2 (the Expedition's route about September 10-23, 1804) (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Thwaites 6, Moulton 8
  - Evans's Map 3 (the Expedition's route about September 23-October 3, 1804) (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Thwaites 7, Moulton 9
  - Evans's Map 4 (the Expedition's route about October 3-14, 1804) (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Thwaites 8-9, Moulton 10
  - Evans's Map 5 (the Expedition's route about October 14-22, 1804) (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Thwaites 10, Moulton 11
  - Evans's Map 6 (the Expedition's route about October 22-November 1, 1804) (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Thwaites 11, Moulton 12
  - Draft of Big White's Map of 1805 by Clark (Box 1, Folder 10r)
    Not in Thwaites, Moulton 31a
  - Big White's Map of 1805 by Clark (Box 1, Folder 10v)
    Thwaites 12, Moulton 31b
  - Evans's Map of 1796-97 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Thwaites 13, Moulton 30
  - Route about April 7-14, 1805 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Thwaites 14-1, Moulton 46
  - Route about April 14-23, 1805 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Thwaites 14-1, Moulton 47
  - Route about April 23-May 3, 1805 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Thwaites 14-1, Moulton 48
  - Route about May 3-9, 1805 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Thwaites 14-1 and 14-2, Moulton 49
  - Route about May 9-19, 1805 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Thwaites 14-2, Moulton 50
  - Route about May 19-25, 1805 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    Thwaites 14-2, Moulton 51
  - Route about May 25-31, 1805 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    Thwaites 14-2 and 14-3, Moulton 52
  - Route about May 31-June 13, 1805 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    Thwaites 14-3, Moulton 53
  - Route about June 13-July 16, 1805 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    Thwaites 14-3, Moulton 54
  - Route about April 7-14, 1805 (Box 1, Folder 21r)
    Thwaites 15, Moulton 33
  - Route about April 14-23, 1805, and Lewis's route about August 10-12, 1806 (Box 1, Folder 21v)
    Thwaites 16, Moulton 34
  - Route about April 20-30, 1805, and Lewis's route about August 7-10, 1806 (Box 1, Folder 22r)
    Thwaites 17, Moulton 35
  - Route about April 29-May 7, 1805, and Lewis's route about August 1-4, 1806 (Box 1, Folder 22v)
    Thwaites 18, Moulton 36
  - Route about May 7-13, 1805, and Lewis's route about August 4-5, 1806 (Box 1, Folder 23r)
    Thwaites 19, Moulton 37
  - Route about May 11-20, 1805, and Lewis's route about August 1-4, 1806 (Box 1, Folder 23v)
    Thwaites 20, Moulton 38
  - Route about May 19-24, 1805, and Lewis's route about July 31-August 1, 1806 (Box 1, Folder 24r)
    Thwaites 21, Moulton 39
  - Route about May 24-30, 1805, and Lewis's route about July 30-31, 1806 (Box 1, Folder 24v)
    Thwaites 23, Moulton 40
  - Area of the junction of the Musselshell and Missouri rivers, route about May 20, 1805 [and] Sketches of falls of the Missouri, route about June-July 1805 (Box 1, Folder 25r)
    Thwaites 22A, Moulton 43 [and] Thwaites 26A, Moulton 45
  - Area of the junction of the Medicine (Sun) and Missouri rivers and sketches of the falls of the Missouri, route about June-July 1805 (Box 1, Folder 25v)
    Thwaites 26, Moulton 44
  - Route about May 29-June 11, 1805, and Lewis's route about July 28-30, 1806 (Box 1, Folder 26r)
    Thwaites 24, Moulton 41
  - Route about June 2-July 10, 1805 (Box 1, Folder 26v)
    Thwaites 25, Moulton 42
  - Route about July 16-21, 1805 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    Thwaites 27, Moulton 62
  - Route about July 21-25, 1805 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    Thwaites 28, Moulton 63
  - Route about July 25-27, 1805 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    Thwaites 29, Moulton 64
  - Route about July 27-August 8, 1805 (Box 1, Folder 30r)
    Thwaites 29, Moulton 65
  - Route about August 8-24, 1805 (Box 1, Folder 30v)
    Thwaites 29A, Moulton 66
  - Route about August 24-September 2, 1805 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    Thwaites 30-1, Moulton 67
  - Route about September 2-9, 1805 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    Thwaites 30-1 and 30-2, Moulton 68
  - Route about September 9-14, 1805 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    Thwaites 30-2, Moulton 69
  - Route about September 13-20, 1805 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    Thwaites 30-2 and 30-3, Moulton 70
  - Route about September 18-October 7, 1805 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    Thwaites 30-3, Moulton 71
  - Route about October 7-11, 1805, and return camps for May 5, 6, and 7, 1806 (Box 2, Folder 36)
    Thwaites 31-1, Moulton 72
  - Route about October 11-13, 1805, and return camps for May 3 and 4, 1806 (Box 2, Folder 37)
    Thwaites 31-1 and 31-2, Moulton 73
  - Route about October 13-15, 1805 (Box 2, Folder 38)
    Thwaites 31-2, Moulton 74
  - Route about October 15-20, 1805, and return camps April 27-30, 1806 (Box 2, Folder 39)
    Thwaites 31-2, Moulton 75
  - Route about October 20-21, 1805, and return camps for April 21, 22, 23, and 24, 1806 (Box 2, Folder 40)
    Thwaites 32-1, Moulton 76
  - Route about October 21-22, 1805, and return camp for April 25, 1806 (Box 2, Folder 41)
    Thwaites 32-1, Moulton 77
  - Route about October 22-30, 1805, and return camps for April 13, 14, 15-17, 19-20, and 21, 1806 (Box 2, Folder 42)
    Thwaites 32-1 and 32-2, Moulton 78
  - Route about October 30-November 4, 1805, and return camps for March 30, March 31-April 6, April 7-8, and 9, 1806 (Box 2, Folder 43)
    Thwaites 32-2, Moulton 79
  - Route about November 4-6, 1805, and return camps for March 27, 28, and 29, 1806 (Box 2, Folder 44)
    Thwaites 32-2, Moulton 80
  - Route about November 6-7, 1805, and return camps for March 25 and 26, 1806 (Box 2, Folder 45)
    Thwaites 32-2 and 32-3, Moulton 81
  - Area of the mouth of the Columbia River, northern side (Box 2, Folder 46)
    Thwaites 32-3, Moulton 82
  - Coastline north of the mouth of the Columbia River (Box 2, Folder 47)
    Thwaites 32-3, Moulton 83
  - Area of the mouth of the Columbia River, southern side (Box 2, Folder 48)
    Thwaites 32-3, Moulton 84
  - Coastline south of the mouth of the Columbia River (Box 2, Folder 49)
    Thwaites 32-3, Moulton 85
  - Draft of the Great Falls and Dalles of Columbia River, route about October 22-29, 1805 (Box 2, Folder 50r)
    Thwaites 33, Moulton 86
  - Draft of the Columbia River, route about October 28-November 4, 1805, and return camps for March 30 and March 31-April 6, 1806 (Box 2, Folder 50v)
    Thwaites 34, Moulton 88
  - Draft of the Columbia River to the Pacific Coast, route for about November 4-14, 1805, and return camps for March 24, 25, 26, 27, 28, and 29, 1806 (Box 2, Folder 51r)
    Thwaites 35, Moulton 89
  - Draft of the mouth of the Columbia River and Haleys Bay [and] Draft of the mouth of the Columbia River and Point William (Box 2, Folder 51v)
    Thwaites 36, Moulton 91 [and] Thwaites 36, Moulton 92
  - Lewis's sketch-map of Vancouver's Island, Nootka Sound, etc. (Box 2, Folder 52)
    Thwaites 37, not in Moulton
  - Draft of the Columbia River, Point Adams, and south along the coast [and] Map from a "Clott Sopp Ind.," about early 1806 (Box 2, Folder 53r)
    Thwaites 38, Moulton 93 [and] Thwaites 39, Moulton 94
  - Draft of the mouth of the Columbia River and fragmented view of the coast (Box 2, Folder 53v)
    Not in Thwaites, Moulton 90
  - Map from a "Shaddot Chief a Chopunnish and a Skillute Several other Indians at the Great Narrows of Columbia on the 18th April 1806" (Box 2, Folder 54r)
    Thwaites 40, Moulton 96
  - Draft of the Columbia River, perhaps the area of the route about October 30-November 1, 1805 (Box 2, Folder 54v)
    Not in Thwaites, Moulton 87
  - Map from "Cut nose and the brother of the twisted hair" on May 8, 1806 (Box 2, Folder 55r)
    Thwaites 41, Moulton 98
  - Map from Hohastillpelp on May 29, 1806 (left side) (Box 2, Folder 55v)
    Thwaites 42, Moulton 99
  - Map from "Sundery Indians of the Chopunnish Nation together" on May 29, 30, and 31, 1806, at "our Camp on the Flat Head River" (Box 2, Folder 56r)
    Thwaites 43, Moulton 101
  - Map from Hohastillpelp on May 29, 1806 (right side) (Box 2, Folder 56v)
    Thwaites 44, Moulton 100
  - Printed form used by Captains during the Expedition: "Thomas Jefferson, President of the United States of America. From the powers vested in us and [blank] by the above authority: To all who shall see these presents, Greeting: Know ye, that from the special confience reposed by us in the sincere and unalterable attachment of chief of the [blank] NATION to the UNITED STATES...." (Box 2, Folder 57r)
  - Route about July 3-8, 1806 (Box 2, Folder 57v)
    Thwaites 45, Moulton 103
  - Route about July 5-9, 1806 (Box 2, Folder 58)
    Thwaites 46, Moulton 104
  - Printed form used by Captains during the Expedition: "Thomas Jefferson, President of the United States of America. From the powers vested in us and [blank] by the above authority: To all who shall see these presents, Greeting: Know ye, that from the special confience reposed by us in the sincere and unalterable attachment of chief of the [blank] NATION to the UNITED STATES...." (Box 2, Folder 59r)
  - Route about July 12-15, 1806 (Box 2, Folder 59v)
    Thwaites 47, Moulton 105
  - Route about July 12-15, 1806 (Box 2, Folder 60)
    Thwaites 48, Moulton 106
  - Route about July 15-18, 1806 (Box 2, Folder 61)
    Thwaites 49, Moulton 107
  - Route about July 18-24, 1806 (Box 2, Folder 62)
    Thwaites 50, Moulton 108
  - Route about July 25-27, 1806 (Box 2, Folder 63)
    Thwaites 51, Moulton 110
  - Route about July 27, 1806 (Box 2, Folder 64)
    Thwaites 52, Moulton 111
  - Route about August 1-2, 1806 (Box 2, Folder 65)
    Thwaites 53, Moulton 112
  - Clark's Map of 1810
    Not in Thwaites, Moulton 125
- Expedition Receipt (WA MSS 304)
  - Receipt for compensation of members of the Expedition (Box 2, Folder 66)
- Other Papers
  - Old labels for Expedition maps (Box 2, Folder 67)